# Department of Political Science 1 Shields Avenue Davis, CA 95616 (253) 227 1483 https://calgara.github.io algaraca calgara@ucdavis.edu Updated: February 25, 2019

# Carlos A. Algara

#### Overview

Expertise American political behavior and legislative politics, collective accountability & congressional representation, congressional elections, quantitative research methods (design and implementation), research design

Research Dimensions of Congressional Representation, Ideological Proximity Voting, Perceptions & Effects of Candidate Valence, Interests Legislative Obstruction, Partisan Polarization & Conflict, Ideal Point Scaling & Estimation, Social Network Analysis

#### Education

present Political Science, *University of California, Davis*, Davis, CA, *PhD Candidate, Expected May 2019*. With focus on American Politics, Comparative Politics, and Political Methodology

Public Policy, Oregon State University, Corvallis, OR, MPP.
 With focus on Social Policy, Applied Policy Analysis, and Mixed Quantitative & Qualitative Methodology

2009 Political Science, Washington State University, Pullman, WA, BA.

# Academic Appointments

2019 - present Lecturer of Political Science, California State University-Sacramento, Sacramento, CA.

#### Peer-Reviewed Publications

Algara, Carlos, and Joseph Zamadics. "The Member Level Determinants & Consequences of Party Legislative Obstruction in the U.S. Senate." *American Politics Research*, 2018, 1–35.

Barnett, George, and Carlos Algara. "Diachronic Equivalence: An Examination of the International News Network." Social Network Analysis & Mining, 2019, 1–11.

Algara, Carlos, and Isaac Hale. "The Distortionary Effects of Racial Animus on Proximity Voting in the 2016 Elections." *Electoral Studies*, In Press. 2019.

Algara, Carlos. "The Conditioning Role of Polarization in U.S. Senate Election Outcomes: A Direct-Election Era & Voter-Level Analysis." *Electoral Studies*, In Press. 2019.

# Dissertation Summary

title Collective Accountability in Congressional Elections: Conditions of Accountability & Implications for Legislative Incentives advisors Walter J. Stone, Erik J. Engstrom, Christopher D. Hare

The dissertation explains the factors that motivate citizen perceptions of the collective job performance of the U.S. Congress and the electoral implications of these perceptions on congressional parties and individual candidates. The central claim is that citizen perceptions of congressional job performance are driven by the nature of collective ideological representation provided by Congress, relative to their own ideological policy preferences, and these perceptions have bearing on the electoral fortunes of the congressional majority party. From this, I specify a model of congressional approval and collective accountability in congressional elections. Using various sources of survey and aggregate data, including an original Cooperative Congressional Election Study module, I evaluate the models and present empirical support for my theory of congressional approval and its effects on electoral accountability and voter turnout.

workshops Dissertation Prospectus and Preliminary Chapter Presented at the 2017 American Political Science Association Dissertation Workshop on U.S. Congressional Politics, led & organized by Jim Curry (Utah) and Danielle Thomsen (Syracuse), in San Francisco, CA, and the 2018 UC Davis Institute for Social Sciences & Humanities Institute Dissertation Workshop.

#### Under Review

Algara, Carlos. "The Partisan & Ideological Determinants of Citizen Congressional Approval." Dissertation Manuscript, September 2018.

# **Working Papers**

- Algara, Carlos. "The Influence of Incumbency, Partisanship, Candidate Quality & National Tides in U.S. Senate Elections, 1914-2016." August 2017.
- Algara, Carlos, and Evan Sandlin (University of California, Davis). "The U.S. Congress and the Israeli Lobby: An Analysis of the Determinants of Congressional Support for Iranian Sanctions." April 2017.
- Algara, Carlos, and Joseph Zamadics (University of Colorado). "Legislative Signaling or Random Error? An Analysis of Spatially Incorrect Voting in Congress." April 2018.
- Algara, Carlos. "Who Goes Public with Whom? A Network Analysis of U.S. Senate Press Events." August 2018.
- Algara, Carlos, and Ross Butters (University of California, Davis). "The Influence of Partisan Polarization and Geographic Neighborhood Context on Congressional Rollcall & Cosponsor Policy Networks." June 2018.
- Algara, Carlos, and Tzu-Ping Liu (University of California, Davis). "The Influence of Partisan Conflict & Policy Responsiveness on Majority Party Electoral Fortunes & Congressional Job Performance: A Time-Series Approach." March 2018.

# Research in Progress

- Algara, Carlos, Samuel Fuller, Christopher Hare, and Cory Struthers. "Are Voters Risk Averse? Specifying Utility Functions in Spatial Models of Voting." *To Be Presented at the 2019 MPSA Annual Meeting*. June 2018.
- Algara, Carlos, and Joseph Broad. "The Role of Partisan Heterogeneity in Candidate Support and Valence Evaluations in the Age of Trump." To Be Presented at the 2019 MPSA Annual Meeting. November 2018.
- Algara, Carlos. "Congressional Job Performance & Negative Voting: The Influence of Congressional Job Approval on Voter Turnout & Majority Party Accountability." Dissertation Manuscript To Be Presented at the 2019 MPSA Annual Meeting. November 2018.

## Research Assistance

- 2017- Co-Investigator, University of Georgia Survey Module, Cooperative Congressional Election Study, w/ Christopher Hare.
- 2017- Graduate Student Researcher, Social & Political Interacting Networks Group, w/ George Barnett (UCD Distinguished Professor of Communications).
- 2019- Graduate Student Researcher, UC Davis Institute of Transporation Studies, Three Revolutions Future Mobility Program.
- 2015 Graduate Student Researcher, "Dataset of 2014 Survey Waves of Freedom Works Supporters", w/ Ronald Rapoport (John Marshall Professor of Political Science, College of William & Mary).
- 2015 Graduate Student Researcher, "Social Network Citation Dataset of State Supreme Court Cases", w/ Robert Huckfeldt.

# Teaching

- 2017 Introduction to American Politics, Graduate Student Instructor of Record, (Summer & Fall).
- 2018 The Scientific Study of Politics: Quantiative Methods, Graduate Teaching Assistant, w/ Christopher Hare, (Spring).
- 2014, 2016 Introduction to American Politics, Graduate Teaching Assistant, w/ Walt Stone, (Fall & Spring).
  - 2015 Introduction to American Politics, Graduate Teaching Assistant, w/ Stuart Hill, (Fall).
  - 2016 Introduction to Comparative Politics, Graduate Teaching Assistant, w/ Ethan Scheiner, (Winter).
  - University of California Center Sacramento Seminar: California State Politics & Policy, Graduate Teaching Assistant, w/ Erik Engstrom, Ben Highton & Scott MacKenzie, (Summer & Fall).
  - 2016 California State Politics & Policy, Graduate Teaching Assistant, w/ Robert Huckfeldt, (Spring).
  - 2015 Introduction to American Public Opinion, Graduate Teaching Assistant, w/ Stuart Hill, (Winter).
  - 2015 Introduction to American Environmental Politics, Graduate Teaching Assistant, w/ Stuart Hill, (Winter, Spring).
  - 2017 Comparative Policymaking, Graduate Teaching Assistant, w/ Matthew Shugart, (Winter).
  - 2017 Democratization, Graduate Teaching Assistant, w/ Gabriella Montinolla, (Spring).
  - 2018 National Security Studies, Graduate Teaching Assistant, w/ Brandon Kinne, (Winter).

- 2010-2012 Introduction to Sociological Research Methods, Graduate Teaching Assistant, w/ Mark Edwards, (OSU).
- 2010-2012 Introduction to Sociology, Graduate Teaching Assistant, w/ Dwaine Plaza (Associate Dean, School of Public Policy), (OSU).
- 2010-2012 Introduction to American Government, Graduate Teaching Assistant, w/ Robert Sahr, (OSU).
- 2010-2012 Introduction to International Environmental Policy, Graduate Teaching Assistant, w/ Brent Steele, (OSU).

#### Grants & Awards

- 2019 Midwest Political Science Association Harrell Rodgers Policy Studies Graduate Student Travel Scholarship, \$500.
- 2018 American Political Science Association Annual Meeting Travel Grant, \$500.
- 2018 National Science Foundation Travel & Workshop Fellowship to the Annual Political Networks Conference, \$900.
- 2018 UC Davis Institute for Social Sciences & Humanities Institute Workshop Retreat, \$500.
- 2018 UC Davis Graduate Student Association Conference Travel Grant, \$500.
- 2016 UC Davis Faculty-Student Summer Collaborative Research Fellowship, w/ Christopher Hare and Walter Stone, \$5,000.
- 2016 Department Travel Grant to Attend the Annual Meeting of the American Political Science Association, \$500.
- 2016, 2017, 2018 Department Travel Grant to Attend the Annual Meeting of the Midwest Political Science Association, \$500.
  - 2013 Fall Graduate Student Fellowship, UC Davis, \$6,000.
  - 2012 School of Public Policy Travel Grant to Attend the Annual Meeting of the Pacific Sociological Association, OSU, \$1,000.
  - 2010-2012 School of Public Policy Masters of Public Policy Fellowship, OSU, Tuition & Stipend.

#### Conference Presentations

- "Are Voters Risk Averse? Specifying Utility Functions in Spatial Models of Voting", MPSA Section Panel, w/ Samuel Fuller, Cory Struthers & Christopher D. Hare, University of California, Davis.
- "The Role of Partisan Heterogeneity in Candidate Support and Valence Evaluations in the Age of Trump", MPSA Section Panel, w/ Joseph Broad, University of California, Davis.
- "Congressional Job Performance & Negative Voting: The Influence of Congressional Job Approval on Voter Turnout & Majority Party Accountability", MPSA Section Panel.
- 2018 "Who Goes Public with Whom? A Network Analysis of U.S. Senate Press Events", *APSA Section Panel*, w/ Christopher P. Donnelly, Drexel University.
- "Network Stability Due to Structural and Diachronic Equivalence: An Examination of the International News Network", Sunbelt Social Networks Conference Section Panel, w/ George Barnett, Distinguished Professor of Communications, University of California, Davis.
- <sup>2018</sup> "The Influence of Partisan Polarization and Geographic Neiborhood Context on Congressional Rollcall & Cosponsor Policy Networks", *PolNet Section Panel*, w/ Ross Butters, University of California, Davis.
- 2018 "The Partisan & Ideological Determinants of Citizen Congressional Approval", MPSA Section Panel.
- <sup>2018</sup> "Legislative Signaling or Random Error? An Analysis of Spatially Incorrect Voting in Congress.", *MPSA Section Panel*, w/ Joe Zamadics, University of Colorado.
- 2018 "The Influence of Partisan Conflict & Policy Responsiveness on Aggregate Majority & Minority Congressional Job Performance: A Time-Series Approach.", WPSA Section Panel, w/ Tzu-Ping Liu, University of California, Davis.
- <sup>2018</sup> "The Distortionary Influence of Racial Animus on Proximity Voting in the <sup>2016</sup> Elections.", WPSA Section Panel, w/ Isaac Hale, University of California, Davis.
- <sup>2017</sup> "The Individual Consequence of Party Legislative Obstruction in the U.S. Senate.", MPSA Section Panel, w/ Joe Zamadics, University of Colorado.
- 2017 "Partisanship, Polarization & Incumbency in U.S. Senate Elections, 1920-2016.", MPSA Section Panel.
- "The U.S. Congress and the Israeli Lobby: An Analysis of the Determinants of Congressional Support for Iranian Sanctions.", WPSA Section Panel, w/ Evan Sandlin, Uniersity of California, Davis.
- 2016 "Collective Accountability in Congressional Elections: An Analysis of Congressional Approval & Ideological Extremity", APSA Section Panel.

- "The Collective "Congress" on the Ballot? An Analysis of Collective Responsibility in Congressional Elections.", MPSA Section Panel.
- 2012 "Irrational Fear or Cause for Concern? The Effects of Hispanic Immigration on Crime Rates in Tucson, AZ.", PSA Section

# Department & Professional Service

- 2017-2018 Legislative Assistant, UC Davis Graduate Student Association, (Funded).
  - American Politics Reading Group/Workshop, Student Co-founder and Organizer, w/ Ross Butters and Christopher Hare, Funded through a \$ 300 grant from the UC Davis Humanties Institute.
  - UCD Associate Instructor Development Certificate, Learner-Centered Teaching. 2016
  - UCD Undergraduate Research Training & Mentorship Program, Mentor, (Funded).
  - Department Representative, Graduate Student Association, UC Davis. 2016
  - Graduate Student Peer Mentor. 2015
- Graduate Student Union Representative, Department of Political Science, UC Davis. 2014-2015
  - Member, American Political Science Association.
  - Member, Midwest Political Science Association.
  - Member, Western Political Science Association.

### Non-Academic Work

- Research Analyst, Oregon State University Foundation, Corvallis, OR.
  - U.S. Sen. Jeff Merkley (D-OR) Graduate Legislative Fellow, Washington, DC.
  - Washington State House of Representatives Undergraduate Legislative Intern, Olympia, WA. 2009

# Computing skills

R (advanced, including data visualization, data mangement, frequentist, SNA & Bayesian Methods), Stata, SPSS Statistical

Collaboration Git/Github, Dropbox/Google Drive

Presentation ETFX(advanced, including Beamer Presentation, Bibtex, & Poster Presentation), RMarkdown (advanced, including typesetting, code replication/collboration, & HTML Web development)

#### References

- University of California, Davis
  - ₩ wstone@ucdavis.edu
- Christopher D. Hare Assistant Professor of Political Sci- George A. Barnett Distinguished Professor of Commuence, University of California, Davis
- Walter J. Stone Professor Emeritus of Political Science, Erik J. Engstrom Professor & Political Science Department Chair, University of California, Davis
  - ₱ ejengstrom@ucdavis.edu
  - nication, University of California, Davis